Inventory of the Papers of Judge John D. Butzner, Jr. 1986-1998
University of Virginia, Arthur J. Morris Law Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
Inventory of the Papers of Judge John D. Butzner, Jr. 1986-1998
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
MSS 00-1
The collection consists of 34 boxes plus a number of bound volumes (18 linear feet).
The Judge John D. Butzner, Jr. papers document his ten years of service, along with two other judges, on the Special Division of the U.S. Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit for the Purpose of Appointing Independent Counsel. While Butzner served, the panel oversaw about twenty-five investigations. His files primarily reflect the panel's supervision of counsels' work, but they also contain correspondence regarding selection of counsel and costs of investigations.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Judge Butzner donated his papers relating to the Office of Independent Counsel to the University of Virginia Law Library in the summer of 2000.
Biographical/Historical Information
Judge John Decker Butzner, Jr., born in Scranton, Pennsylvania in 1917, received a B.A. from the University of Scranton in 1938 and an LL.B. from the University of Virginia in 1941. After law school graduation he went into private practice in Fredericksburg for a brief time and then joined the U.S. Air Force in 1942. After the war he returned to his Fredericksburg practice where he remained until his 1958 appointment to the Judicial Circuit Court of Virginia.
In 1962 President John F. Kennedy appointed Butzner to the U.S. District Court of Eastern Virginia. Five years later President Lyndon B. Johnson appointed him to the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit. Judge Butzner assumed senior status in 1982, and five years after that, Chief Justice William H. Rehnquist asked him to serve as a member of the Special Division of the U.S. Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit for the Purpose of Appealing Independent Counsel. Judge Butzner served for ten years in that post.
From 1988 to 1998 Judge Butzner worked and corresponded with Judges Wilbur F. Bell, Peter T. Fay, George E. MacKinnon, David B. Sentelle, and Joseph T. Sneed. He also had some correspondence with Attorneys General Dick Thornburgh and Janet Reno. Independent counsels serving during this time include Arlin M. Adams, David M. Barrett, Carol Elder Bruce, Joseph DiGenova, James C. McKay, Daniel S. Pearson, Whitney North Seymour, Jr., Donald C. Smaltz, Kenneth R. Starr, Lawrence Walsh, and Dan K. Webb.
Scope and Content Information
The correspondence between the judges reflects the workings of their panel, their method of selecting independent counsel, various revisions of the Ethics in Government Act of 1978, and the high costs of the investigations.
People or matters under investigation during this period included Bruce R. Babbitt, Secretary of the Interior; Ronald H. Brown, Secretary of Commerce; Lauro F. Cavazos; Henry Cisneros, Secretary of Housing and Urban Development; Michael D. Deaver, White House aide; Raymond J. Donovan, Secretary of Labor; Alphonse Michael (Mike) Espy, Secretary of Agriculture; Madison Guaranty Savings and Loan Association, better known as "Whitewater;" Janet G. Mullins, regarding the handling of President William Clinton's passport files; Franklyn L. Nofzinger and Edward Meese III; Oliver L. North in the Iran-Contra affair, Theodore B. Olson, Assistant Attorney General; and Samuel R. Pierce.
The largest case concerns Oliver L. North and the sale of arms to Iran. Included are files regarding President Ronald Reagan's and President George Bush's applications for attorney's fees resulting from that investigation. There is also extensive information on the case regarding Janet Mullins and the search of President William Clinton's passport files, and on the Madison Guaranty Savings and Loan case, better known as Whitewater, as well as the controversial appointment of Kenneth R. Starr to serve as independent counsel in that case.
Arrangement
The files are organized alphabetically by case name and consist of extensive correspondence between the judges; memoranda, orders and opinions; reports of the independent counsel; applications for attorneys' fee; and other related documents.
Contents List
- Butzner Appointment to the special division of the U.S. Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit for the purpose of appointing independent counsel 1988-1998 (Box 1)
  Correspondence between judges
- Candidates for Independent Counsel: A-Z 1992-1997 (Box 1)
  List and biographies; some correspondence
- Correspondence between Judges Butzner, MacKinnon, Sneed, Sentelle, and Fay 1988-1990, 9 folders (Box 1-3)
  Correspondence covers a range of matters including indictments, investigation procedures, revision of the Ethics in Government Act, attorneys fees, etc.; some of this correspondence relates to the major cases.
- [Independent Counsel]: Special Division's Powers to Define the Jurisdiction of the Independent Counsel. n.d., 1990 (Box 3)
- In re Bruce Edward Babbit: application for appointment of independent counsel 1997-1998 (Box 3)
  Memoranda and correspondence between judges; motions and orders
- In re Ronald H. Brown: appointment of independent counsel 1995-1996, 4 folders (Box 3)
- In re Ronald H. Brown: interview with Lt. Col. Cogswell 1997, 12/11/97 video-cassette (Box 3)
- In re Ronald H. Brown: Lisa M. Brannock application for attorney's fees 1996-1997 (Box 4)
  Memoranda between jugdes; orders
- In re Ronald H. Brown: Nolanda S. Hill application for attorney's fees 1996-1997 (Box 4)
  Memoranda between judges; orders
- In re Ronald H. Brown: Kenneth C. White application for attorney's fees 1996-1997 (Box 4)
- In re Lauro Cavazos: appointment of independent counsel and final report 1990-1992 (Box 4)
- In re James William Cicconi: appointment of independent counsel 1989-1990 (Box 4)
  Application for attorney's fees, memoranda and correspondence between judges; orders
- In re Henry Cisneros: appointment of independent counsel 1994-1995, 4 folders (Box 5)
  Memoranda and correspondence between judges; orders
- In re T. Kenneth Cribb, Jr.: preliminary investigation 1989 (Box 5)
  Order
- In re Michael K. Deaver: Report of independent counsel, 2 folders (Box 6-7)
  Orders
- In re Edward J. Derwinski: notification of initiation of of preliminary investigation 1989 (Box 6-7)
- In re Raymond J. Donovan: application for attorney's fees 1987, 4 folders (Box 6-7)
  Memoranda and correspondence between judges
- In re Raymond J. Donovan: independent counsel's report 1987 (Box 7)
- In re Alphonse Michael (Mike) Espy: appointment of independent counsel 1990-1999, 14 folders (Box 7-10)
  Correspondence and memoranda between judges and independent counsel; pleadings, motions, orders
- In re Albert Gore, Jr: notification of preliminary investigation 1997-1998 (Box 10)
  Memoranda between judges; orders and motions
- In re F. Henry Habicht II: preliminary investigation 1989 (Box 10)
- In re Alexis M. Herman: appointment of independent counsel 1997-1998 (Box 10)
  Memoranda between judges; motions and orders
- In re Inslaw, Inc./Meese: memoranda, correspondence, reports of independent counsel; 1988-1992 (Box 10)
  Orders and opinions. [See also Edwin Meese III]
- In re Madison Guaranty Savings and Loan Association (MGSLA) [Whitewater]: appointment of independent counsel 1994-1998, 8 folders (Box 11-12)
  Correspondence and memoranda between judges; correspondence between independent counsel and Justice Department; orders, notices, judicial complaints
- In re MGSLA: candidates for appointment of independent counsel in Whitewater investigation 1994-1998, 2 folders (Box 12)
  Correspondence between judges; miscellaneous correspondence; newspaper clippings
- In re MGSLA: Dow Jones & Co., Inc. petition to disclose report of independent counsel Robert B. Fiske 1994 (Box 13)
  Orders, motions, memoranda and correspondence between judges
- In re MGSLA: Peter Heller correspondence 1994-1998 (Box 13)
- In re MGSLA: Referral to the U.S. House of Representatives Pursuant to Title 28, U.S. Code, Â§595(c) Submiited by the Office of Independent Counsel Kenneth W. Starr 1998, September 9 (Box 13)
- In re MGSLA: release of report on the death of Vincent W. Foster, Jr. to public 1997 (Box 13)
  Miscellaneous letters urging judges to release the report
- In re MGSLA: report on the death of Vincent W. Foster, Jr. 1997, 3 folders (Box 13)
- In re MGSLA: reports of independent counsel Robert B. Fiske, Jr.--In Re Contacts between the White House and Treasury Regarding RTC's Investigation 1994 October 6, 2 folders (Box 14)
- In re Edwin Meese III: application for attorney's fees 1985-1989, 1 folder and 2 volumes (Box 14)
  Correspondence between judges; opinion; see also Nofzinger file
- In re Janet Mullins: appointment of independent counsel 1992-1995, 3 folders (Box 15)
  Memoranda and correspondence between judges; orders, motions, briefs; comments re final report of independent counsel
- [In re Janet Mullins]: Special Inquiry into the search and retrieval of William Clinton's Passport Files 1992 (Box 15)
- In re Janet Mullins: Final Report of Independent Counsel Joseph E. DiGenova 1995, 3 folders (Box 16-17)
- In re Janet Mullins: Final Report of Independent Counsel Joseph E. DiGenova. Appendix 1995, 3 folders (Box 16-17)
- In re Janet Mullins: Final Report of Independent Counsel Joseph E. DiGenova. Witness Directory 1995 (Box 16-17)
- In re Janet Mullins: Response of Steven K. Barry to Final Report of Independent Counsel Joseph E. DiGenova 1995 (Box 16-17)
- U.S. Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit. Final Report and Sealed Index of the Independent Counsel in re: Janet G. Mullins 1995, Nov. 30, 3 bound volumes (Box 16-17)
- In re: Janet Mullins: application for attorney's fees 1995-1996 (Box 18)
  Memoranda and correspondence between judges; opinion
- In re Janet Mullins: Memorandum of Points and Authorities in Support of Petition for Reimbursement of Attorney's Fees and Costs 1995, Bound volume (Box 18)
- In re Janet Mullins: Reply Memoranda of Janet. G. Mullins... 1996, 2 bound volumes (Box 18)
- In re Janet Mullins: Steven K. Berry application for attorney's fees 1995-1996, 2 folders (Box 18)
  Memoranda and correspondence between judges, orders and opinions
- In re Janet Mullins: Elizabeth M. Tamposi application for attorney's fees 1995 (Box 18)
  Orders and opinions
- In re Janet Mullins: Margaret DeB. Tutwiler application for attorney's fees 1995, 2 folders (Box 18)
  Memoranda and correspondence between judges; orders and opinion
- In re Franklyn L. Nofzinger/Edwin Meese III: application for attorney's fees 1988-1992, 3 folders (Box 19)
  Memoranda and correspondence between judges; orders and opinions
- In re Oliver L. North: Walsh show-cause order 1986-1993 (Box 20)
  Memoranda and letters between judges; pleadings and orders
- In re Oliver L. North: memoranda and letters between judges; copies of petitions and orders concerning access to the final report 1988-1998, 3 folders (Box 20)
- In re Oliver L. North: Walsh's interim and financial reports to Congress 1988-1993, 2 folders (Box 20)
  Memoranda and letters between judges; petitions and orders
- In re Oliver L. North: Lawrence E. Walsh expenditures 1989-1994 (Box 21)
- In re Oliver L. North: motions, primarily from Ronald W. Reagan, Edwin Meese III, and North, concerning the release of the final report 1988-1998, 3 folders (Box 21)
- In re Oliver L. North: Fourth Interim Report to Congress by Lawrence E. Walsh, Independent Counsel for Iran/Contra Matters 1993, Feb. 8, 2 volumes (Box 21)
- In re Oliver L. North: Final Report of the Independent Counsel for the Iran/Contra Matters 1993, Aug. 3, 4 volumes (Box 21)
- In re Oliver L. North: comments and responses on Final Report of Independent Counsel A-Z 1993, Dec., 4 folders (Box 22)
  Comments from Edwin Meese III, Simon Peres, Colin L. Powell, Ronald W. Reagan, Casper W. Weinberger and others
- In re Oliver L. North: James L. Adkins application for reimbursement of attorney's fees 1994; 1988-1993 (Box 23)
  Memoranda, orders and opinion
- In re Oliver L. North: Richard L. Armitage application for attorney's fees 1993-1995, 2 folders (Box 23)
  Memoranda and orders
- In re Oliver L. North: George Bush application for attorney's fees 1993-1995, 2 folders (Box 23)
- In re Oliver L. North: George Cave application for attorney's fees 1994-1995 (Box 23)
  Orders and opinion
- In re Oliver L. North: Edwin G. Corr application for attorney's fee 1994-1995 (Box 23)
- In re Oliver L. North: Robert C. Dutton application for attorney's fees 193-1994, 2 folders (Box 24)
  Correspondence between judges; memoranda, opinions
- In re Oliver L. North: William Dwyer application for attorney's fees 1994-1997 (Box 24)
- In re Oliver L. North: Joseph F. Fernandez application for attorney's fees 1994, 2 folders (Box 24)
  Memoranda and correspondence between judges; opinions
- In re Oliver L. North: Richard B. Gadd application for attorney's fees 1992-1993 (Box 24)
  Correspondence between judges; opinions
- In re Oliver L. North: Norman H. Gardner, Jr. application for attorney's fees 1993-1994, 2 folders (Box 25)
- In re Oliver L. North: H. Lawrence Garrett III appliation for attorney's fees 1994-1995 (Box 25)
- In re Oliver L. North: Clair E. George application for attorney's fees 1994, 2 folders (Box 25)
- In re Oliver L. North: Donald P. Gregg application for attorney's fees 1994-1995 (Box 25)
  Memoranda and correspondence between judges; opinion and orders
- In re: Oliver L. North: William Haskell application for attorney's fees 1995 (Box 25)
  Memoranda and opinion
- In re Oliver L. North: William G. Langton and Robert H. Mason application for attorney's fees 1994, Memoranda and correspondence between judges; order and opinion (Box 26)
- In re Oliver L. North: Ambassador Nicholas Platt application for attorney's fees 1994 (Box 26)
  Memoranda, order, and opinion
- [In re Oliver L. North]: Walter Raymond, Jr., Otto Reich and Glenn A. Robinette applications for attorney's fees 1988-1992 (Box 26)
- In re Oliver L. North: Ronald W. Reagan application for attorney's fees 1993-1996, 3 folders (Box 26)
- In re Oliver L. North: Donald T. Regan application for attorney's fees 1995 (Box 27)
- In re Oliver L. North: Vincent Shields and Jerry Gruner joint application for attorney's fees 1994-1995 (Box 27)
- In re Oliver L. North: George P. Schultz application for attorney's fees 1992, 3 folders (Box 27)
- In re Oliver L. North: Howard R. Teicher application for attorney's fees 1991-1995, 2 folders (Box 27-28)
  Memoranda and correspondence between judges; orders and opinions; correspondence between attorneys and Department of Justice
- In re Oliver L. North: William G. Walker application for attorney's fees 1995 (Box 28)
- In re Oliver L. North: Samuel J. Watson application for attorney's fees 1992-1993 (Box 28)
  Memoranda and correspondence between judges; order and opinion
- In re Theodore B. Olson: application for attorney's fees 1998-1989 (Box 28-29)
- In re Theodore B. Olson: motions and report of independent counsel 1988, 5 folders (Box 28-29)
- In re Theodore B. Olson: Affadavits and Exhibits in Support of Petition for Recovery of Attorney's Fees and Costs 1988, 2 volumes (Box 30)
- In re Theodore B. Olson: Robert M. Perry application for attorney's fees 1988 (Box 30)
- In re Samuel Pierce, Jr.: appointments of independent counsels; IC financial statements and final report 1996, 6 folders (Box 30-31)
  Correspondence and memoranda between judges; notices, motions and orders; press releases
- In re Samuel Pierce, Jr: Final Report of Independent Counsel 1998 October 27, 3 volumes (Box 32)
- In re Samuel Pierce, Jr.: Petition for reimbursement of attorney's fees and costs 1998, 1 volume (Box 32)
- In re Samuel Pierce: Ernest Olivas, Jr. application for attorney's fees 1995-1998 (Box 32)
- In re Eli J. Segal: appointment of independent counsel 1995-1997, 4 folders (Box 32-33)
- In re George T. Trent: preliminary investigation 1997 (Box 32-33)
  Notifications; memoranda and correspondence between judges; termination of investigation
- In re Henk Visser: petition for appointment of special prosecutor 1989-1990, 3 folders (Box 32-33)
- In re Milton Lawrence Wallace: application for attorney's fees; report of independent counsel 1987, 2 folders (Box 34)
- In re William F. Weld: preliminary investigation; order 1988 (Box 34)
- Memoranda and research material prepared by Butzner clerks 1986-1998 (Box 34)
- News stories re independent counsel and special judicial panel 1997-1998 (Box 34)
- Removing Conflicts from the Administration of Justice: Conflicts of Interest and Independent Counsels under the Ethics in Government Act. Georgetown Law Journal, Vol. 79, No. 1 1990 October (Box 34)
- Sixty-Seventh Judicial Conference of the Fourth Circuit: T he Independent Counsel Process: Is It Broken and How Should It Be Fixed? Washington and Lee Law Review, Vol. 54, No. 4 1997 Fall, 2 copies (Box 34)